Inventory of the Austin-Twyman Papers, 1765-1939
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Austin-Twyman Papers, 1765-1939.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 69 Au7
10,706 items.
Papers of the Austin, Twyman, Spiller and Horsley families of Amherst and Buckingham Counties, Virginia.
Austin family,; Twyman family,; Horsley family,; Spiller family,; Peter Francisco,; Archibald Austin.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Purchased: 10,706 items, 1969.
Biographical/Historical Information
Archibald Austin (1772-1837) was born in Buckingham County, Virginia. He practiced law in Buckingham County until being elected as a member of the Virginia State House of Delegates, 1815-1816, 1835-1837. He served as a Democrat to the fifteeth Congress, 1817-1819 and also as a presidential elector on the Democratic ticket in 1832 and 1836. He and his wife, Grace R. (Booker) Austin had several children including the following: James M. Austin, John Austin, Bernard Austin, Martha E. (Austin) Twyman, Grace Austin and Frances (Austin) Wright.
Archibald Austin's son-in-law, Doctor Iverson Lewis Twyman (1810-1864) married first, Mary Lavinia Horsley and second, Martha E. Austin. Their children were Iverson Lewis Twyman, Jr. (1849-1921); John Austin Twyman, Superintendent of Schools in Buckingham County; Samuel Rogers Twyman; Augusta Giles Twyman and Mabel Booker Twyman. James Madison Spiller was the father-in-law of Iverson Lewis Twyman, Jr.
Additional biographical and genealogical information is interspersed throughout this collection.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1765 (1800-1890) 1939, of the Austin, Twyman, Spiller and Horsley families of Amherst and Buckingham counties, Va. The papers include correspondence, accounts, legal papers and manuscript volumes. Includes papers of Archibald Austin (1772-1837), member of Congress, 1817-1819, member of the Virginia House of Delegates, 1815-1816, 1835-1837, his wife, Grace R. (Booker) Austin and their children, James M. Austin, John Austin and Bernard Austin, Grace Austin and Frances (Austin) Wright. Correspondents of Archibald Austin include William H. Cabell, Walter L. Fontaine, Charles Yancey, Waller Taylor, George Booker, and Robert T. Hubard. Subjects include the War of 1812, national politics and the business of the Virginia General Assembly. Papers include correspondence of Archibald Austin's son-in-law, Doctor Iverson Lewis Twyman (1810-1864) who married first, Mary Lavinia Horsley and second, Martha E. Austin. His correspondence concerns slavery, farm management, the study and practice of medicine and the education of his children whose letters are also part of the collection. His children were Iverson Lewis Twyman (1849-1921), John Austin Twyman, Superintendent of Schools in Buckingham County, Samuel Rogers Twyman (concerning Twyman genealogy), Augusta Giles Twyman and Mabel Booker Twyman.
Papers also contain a few items concerning the Horsley family and much correspondence and many accounts of James Madison Spiller, a friend of Dr. Iverson Lewis Twyman and the father-in-law of Iverson Lewis Twyman, Jr. The collection includes several items relating to Peter Francisco, Revolutionary War hero; materials relating to the James River and Kanawha Canal; letters pertaining to the Civil War; accounts and legal documents concerning Albemarle, Amherst, Appomattox, Botetourt, Buckingham, Campbell, Cumberland, Goochland, King and Queen, Nelson, Powhatan and Prince Edward Counties; genealogical materials relating to the Austin, Booker, Byrd, Clark, Gaines, Lewis, Montague, Rogers, Twyman and Walker families; and miscellaneous material consisting of poetry, religious manuscripts, recipes, memoranda and photographs.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection is organized into 5 series: Series 1 contains letters, Series 2 contains the James River and Kanawha Company papers, Series 3 contains accounts and legal papers, Series 4 contains genealogical material, and Series 5 contains manuscript volumes.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into series and then subseries. These subseries are arranged by family names, then by individual name and finally by date.
Index of Slavery and African-American Materials
An index to materials relating to slavery and to African Americans in the Austin-Twyman Papers has been filed with the inventory and is located within the first box of this collection.
Index
Slave Letters: Folder 3 - Susan Austin Folder 13 - Mary to Mother Folder 13 - Lucy Patterson to Beverley Folder 16 - London Folder 47 - Absalom Folder 50 - Cambridge Austin Folder 155 - Anita Blew Folder 156 - Ben Folder 63 - Sue Asa Washington (former slave?)
Slave - Beverley: Folder 11 - Payment for hire of slave Beverley while he was in the woods Folder 12 Folder 13 - Letter Lucy Patterson to Beverley Folder 24 - Hire of slave Beverly and taking him to trader to see how much he would give for him to know whether to sell him or hire him out Folder 49 - Runaway hired hand Beverley and service of slaves at Tredegar and Confederate States Government Folder 53 - Slave Beverley with army during Gettysburg campaign
Blacks: Folder 96 - Jeanes Fund for black teachers
Children: Folder 23 - Care of a slave's child while she is in the field Folder 28 - Sale of a slave child
Civil War Service: Folder 53 - Tredegar and Confederate States Government hiring of slaves Folder 255 - Receipt, 1864, for slave to work on fortifications Folder 62 - Confederate States Army hire Folder 156 - Ben working on Richmond defenses (1864) Folder 156 - Names of those 18-53 years old (1864)
Free Blacks: Folder 138 - Settling blacks in Ohio
Freedmen: Folder 54 - Sharecropping with freed blacks Folder 63 - Sue Asa Washington (former slave ?) letter Folder 68 - Texas and blacks Folder 75 - Buckingham "Re-adjusters all over the county voted for [Shed Dungee, a black candidate] and John Eldridge says he is prouder of that one act than of any other in his whole life." lists others who voted for Dungee Folder 83 - Lynching in Texas (1878)
Health: Folder 39 - Gonorrhea Folder 44 - Illness Folder 45 - Illness Folder 47 - Health Folder 62 - Chloride of lime to prevent fever
Hiring: Folder 11 - Payment for hire of slave Beverley while he was in woods Folder 12 - Hiring and selling of slaves Folder 17 - Hiring out of slaves Folder 18 Folder 21 - Hiring slaves to work on railroad Folder 24 - Taking slave trader to get price to know whether to hire a slave Folder 26 Folder 27 Folder 36 - (1846) Folder 40 - (1850) Folder 41 - (1851) Folder 43 - (1853) Folder 44 - (1854) To work on railroad Folder 45 - (1855) To lay railroad track Folder 46 - (1856-1858) Folder 47 - (1859-1860) Folder 48 - (1861-1862) Folder 49 - (1863-1864) Folder 50 - (n.d.) Folder 155
Ideology: Folder 126 - Qualms of someone concerning slavery
Lynching: Folder 83
Marriage: Folder 13 - Letter, 7 May 1859, of R. Eldridge stating he has no objection to a slave marriage and endorsing the prospective husband Folder 40 - Letter, 1850, of W. C. Jordan granting permission for his slave to marry one of Twyman's slaves if Twyman approves Folder 53 - Letter, 13 September 1853, of Martha E. (Austin) Twyman concerning slave leaving to visit his wife Folder 64 - Slave marriage
Occupations: Folder 12 - Slaves weaving cloth and making shoes Folder 44- 45, 47-49 - Working on railroad (Virginia and Tennessee) Folder 45, 47 - Working on James River and Kanawha Canal Folder 49 - Tredegar Folder 46 - Slave nurse Folder 53, 62, 156, 255 - Civil War Service Folder 133 - "I did not intend you to make a cook of Sally. Please leave her to herself to attend to the cows and her business - the women who suckle can and must cook."
Profitability: See also entries under hiring and sale. Folder 13 - "If we lose when we own the Negroes, how much more loss we would sustain when Negroes are hired/sale of 43 slaves in 12 years Folder 14 - Prices in Richmond (1854) Folder 23 - Loss of slave mourned as a loss of property and loss as family member Folder 24 - Taking slave trader to get value to know whether to sell or hire Folder 32 - Buying slaves in Richmond and taking them south
Recalcitrance: Folder 51 - Alleged malingering and burglarizing female slave Folder 62 - Verbal abuse by slave
Religion: Folder 152-153 - Permissions to join Mulberry Grove Baptist Church
Resistance: Folder 40 - Poisoning
Runaways: Folder 11 - Payment for hire of slave Beverley while he was in woods Folder 21 - Runaway slave Folder 45 - Runaway of hired slave from James River and Kanawha Canal Folder 46 - Sale of runaway slave, runaway hired slave
Sale: Folder 11 - Possible sale of slaves to pay off debt Folder 12 - Hiring and selling of slaves Folder 14 - Sale of slaves in Richmond, price of slaves in Richmond (1854) Folder 23 - Hiding forthcoming sale, "[?] will tell the Negroes and set them to crying and howling Folder 24 - Taking slave to trader to get value to know whether to sell or hire him Folder 25 - Selling of slaves Folder 28 - Sale of slave child and selling Folder 31 - Improving appearance before sale Folder 32 - Buying slaves in Richmond and taking them south Folder 38 - Evaluating slaves Folder 39 - Slave trader, Samuel Rees Folder 42 - Asking for slave to be delivered so she can be sent south with others Folder 44 - Evaluation Folder 45 - Value Folder 46 - Sale of runaway slave Folder 49 - Price Folder 50 - Value Folder 51 - Fixing clothes to sell a slave in, fixing up slaves (improving appearance) to sell and selling slaves Folder 53 - Dressing up slaves to sell them Folder 134 - Buying and selling Folder 138 - Disposition of slaves Folder 155 - Selling of slave girls Folder 165 - Form of bill of sale of slave Folder 249 - Account of sale (1858) of Negro man Folder 339 - Slave estate of a Benjamin Harrison
Slavetraders: Folder 38, 42,155 - Seth Woodruff Folder 39 - Samuel Rees Folder 44 - R. H. Dickinson & Bro. Folder 45 - Dickinson, Hill & Co. Folder 49 - Hill, Dickinson & Co. Folder 45 - Pulliam & Davis Folder 249 - Pulliam (D. M.) & Co.
Slaves - Status: Folder 23 - Loss of slave mourned as loss of property and as loss of member of family Folder 42 - Asking someone to be protector and advisor to a slave
Teachers: Folder 96 - Jeanes Fund for black teachers
Treatment and Punishment: Folder 43 - Punishment of slave Folder 46 - Hire of slave and his treatment Folder 51 - Sewing slave clothing Folder 165 - Draft of note concerning whipping of slav
Index Terms
Family Names:
Austin family.; Horsley family.; Spiller family.; Twyman family.
Persons:
Francisco, Peter, d. 1831.; Austin, Archibald, 1772- 1837.
Subjects:
Virginia. General Assembly.; Slavery--Virginia--19th century.; Medicine--Study and teaching.; United States-- History-- Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--History--War of 1812.
Geographical Names:
James River and Kanawha Canal.; Buckingham County (Va.)--History.; Amherst County (Va.)--History.
Occupations:
Medicine--Practice- -Virginia.
Components List
  Series 1: Letters
- Letters, 1765-1939. (Folder 1-159)
  Letters are filed in chronological order within each folder. Consequently, there may be more than one letter in the folder written by the person listed in the inventory and also, the letters written by this person may not be filed together within the folder. If the researcher is interested in a person, look throughout the folder. If the researcher is interested in a subject, each letter by the person writing about the subject must be looked at make sure all of the information about the subject has been seen.
  This series is divided into subseries by family name.
  - Letters to, from, or about the Austin Family, 1800-1888, n.d. (Folder 1-21)
    - Archibald Austin, 1808-1837., 22 items. (Folder 1-2)
      - Letters by Archibald Austin, 1812-1820., 5 items. (Folder 1)
        Includes letters to Thomas Leland, John Austin (concerning a survey of James Breckenridge's grant). William A. Perkins and Robert Garland.
      - Letters by family to Archibald Austin, 1808-1837., 17 items. (Folder 2)
        Includes letters by James Austin (brother, concerning candidates for House of Delegates in election of 1837), Grace R. Austin (wife), James M. Austin (son, concerning candidates for House of Delegates in election of 1837), Bernard Austin (son, while studying at an unidentified college which he compares to Hampden-Sydney College; and concerning his law practice and that of his father; and politics), John Austin (son).
    - The Archibald Austins, 1800-1853, n.d., 72 items. (Folder 3-8)
      - Letters by family to the Archibald Austins, 1840-1853, n.d., 11 items. (Folder 3)
        Includes letters by Bernard Austin (to his mother asserting his independence in regard to a marriage choice and concerning his leaving Virginia), B. G. Booker (brother of Mrs. Austin, concerning his move to the West), I. L. Twyman (asking assent from Grace R. Austin to marry her daughter), Eliza B. Austin, Susan Austin (slave), Martha E. (Austin) Twyman.
      - Letters by others to the Archibald Austins, 1800-1815., 8 items. (Folder 4)
        Includes letters by James Walker (concerning inoculation), William H. Cabell, Waller Taylor, Thomas McCleland (sending French clover seed from Botetourt Co., Va.), Jeremiah Weaver (money owed for a racehorse and carriage horses), Samuel P. Christian (soldiers from Buckingham County stationed on Craney Island in War of 1812), George Booker (written 26 March 1814, while serving with troops east of Lynnhaven), Gideon Spencer (asking Archibald Austin to run for Congress).
      - Letters by others to the Archibald Austins, 1820-1829., 19 items. (Folder 5)
        Includes letters by Richard Dabbs (setting up a schedule for preaching), Charles Yancey (written 10 February 1820, concerning session of General Assembly and the Missouri Compromise), Waller Taylor ([several items] Florida Question; Missouri Compromise; death of Stephen Decatur; insanity of John Randolph of Roanoke; Daniel D. Tompkins; opinion of Henry Clay; fear of Jackson and Calhoun; and election of John Q. Adams), Walter L. Fontaine (written 30 January 1821, concerning business of the General Assembly), Ro. B. Jones, Isham Talbot (laying off the town of Tuscaloosa, Alabama; description of Alabama; his crops), S. Branch, Samuel C. Scott, John Fauntieroy, A. Caldwell.
      - Letters by others to the Archibald Austins, 1830-1834., 12 items. (Folder 6)
        Includes letters by A. White, Hampden-Sydney College (monthly report), George Booker (concerning business of General Assembly and revision of Virginia Court System in 1831), Stephen Hubbard, E. Booker (concerning anti-tariff convention to be held in Philadelphia September 1821), J. Mills, C. Fontaine, John W. Haskins, Samuel Ford, James W. Bouldin.
      - Letters by others to the Archibald Austins, 1835., 11 items. (Folder 7)
        Includes letters by George Booker (declining to run again for House of Delegates), Charles Yancey (declining to run again for House of Delegates), John Morgan (asking Archibald Austin to run for House of Delegates), James Bouldin (discussing his mailing list to constituents), M. C. Spencer, P. P. Smith, Stephen Hubbard, C. Fontaine, H. Lipscomb, Samuel Ford.
      - Letters by others to the Archibald Austins, 1836-1850, n.d., 11 items. (Folder 8)
        Includes letters by P. P. Smith, P. H. Fontaine (news of politics in Washington and Virginia in 1836), Ro. T. Hubard, Thomas McCoy (concerning Bernard G. Austin), W. P. Mosley, University of Virginia (monthly report), Thomas H. Merryman, W. C. Nicholas.
    - Archibald Austin, Jr., 1843-1862., 7 items. (Folder 9)
      Letters by Archibald Austin, Jr.
    - Bernard Gaines Austin, 1840-1856., 17 items. (Folder 10)
      Letters by (and to) Bernard Gaines Austin. Concerning his life in Missouri; and an operation by Doctor [John Peter] Mettauer. To brothers and to Dr. I. L. Twyman.
    - Fances (Austin) Wright, 1847-1881, n.d., 111 items. (Folder 11-13)
      - Letters by Frances (Austin) Wright, 1849-1881., 29 items. (Folder 11)
        Payment for hire of slave Beverly while he was in the woods. Possible sale of slaves to pay off debt. Letters written to John Austin while he was attending the University of Virginia. Family going to the Centennial on borrowed money. News of the centennial. Reconstruction.
      - Letters by Frances (Austin) Wright, n.d., 64 items. (Folder 12)
        Concerning a homesick overseer, preparations for Christmas; food; clothes; hiring and selling of slaves; plants for the yard; slaves weaving cloth and making shoes. Slave Beverly.
      - Letters by others to Frances (Austin) Wright, 1847-1871, n.d., 18 items. (Folder 13)
        Includes two slave letters (Mary to her mother and father; and Lucy Patterson to Beverly, her son). Includes letter, 7 May 1859, of R. Elariage stating he has no objection to a slave marriage and endorsing the prospective husband. Letter outlining how to manage the estate of Archibald Austin ['If we lose when we own the negroes, how much more loss we would sustain when the negroes are hired."] and what has transpired financially since Austin's death twelve years previously including the sale of forty-three slaves. Also letters written from Virginia Female Institute, Staunton, Va.
    - George B. Austin, 1848-1888, n.d., 14 items. (Folder 14)
      Letters by George B. Austin. Also 2 letters to George B. Austin, 1847 and 1853. Sale of slaves; price of slaves in Richmond in 1854 and Austin's life as a schoolteacher in West Virginia.
    - Grace Austin, 1864-1865, n.d., 6 items. (Folder 15)
      Letters to Grace Austin. Hiring of slaves in February 1865; and religion.
    - John Austin, 1845-1850, n.d., 26 items. (Folder 17-18)
      - Letters by John Austin, 1850-1851., 12 items. (Folder 17)
        Studying medicine at the University of Virginia and at Philadelphia College of Medicine. Hiring out of slaves.
      - Letters by others to John Austin, 1845-1851, n.d., 14 items. (Folder 18)
        Letters written by J. L. Cabell (describing location of rooms at University of Virginia and recommending Austin), Charles J. Gee (concerning studying medicine and University of Virginia) and Thomas W. Hix (concerning studies at Philadelphia College of Medicine). Hiring of slaves.
    - Martha Austin, 1840-1848, n.d., 5 items. (Folder 19)
      Letters to Martha Austin, (before her marriage in 1848 to I.L. Twyman - see that file). Letter describing wedding plans and a cap.
    - Thomas Austin, 1838-1875, n.d., 29 items. (Folder 20-21)
      - Letters by Thomas Austin, 1853-1875., 11 items. (Folder 20)
        Family rift. Letters, 25 July - 5 September 1861, written by Austin while serving in [Company E, 21st Virginia Infantry Regiment.]
      - Letters to Thomas Austin, 1838-1870, n.d., 18 items. (Folder 21)
        Includes letter about civil War, 1861, from S. E. Austin, wife of Dr. James M. Austin and letters, 1838, written by Thomas F. Perkins concerning University of Virginia. Other letters concern hiring slaves to work on railroad and runaway slave.
  - Letters to, from, or about the Twyman Family, 1811-1937, n.d. (Folder 22-125)
    - Iverson L. Twyman, 1829-1864., 513 items. (Folder 22-50)
      - Letters by Iverson L. Twyman (1810-1864) of Amherst and Buckingham Co., Virginia, 1838-1839., 6 items. (Folder 22)
        Includes letters to Miss Mary Lavinia Horsley (1838), Mrs. Mary Lavinia Horsley Twyman, capt. Robert Horsley, Miss Rebecca P. Horsley. (See letter, 4 March 1839, to Lavinia Horsley concerning eastern Tennessee).
      - Letters by Iverson L. Twyman (1810-1864), 1840-1848., 16 items. (Folder 23)
        Includes letters to Capt. A. W. Flippin, Capt. Harrington, George B. Austin, Martha E. Austin (written during her engagement to Twyman), Mrs. Martha E. Twyman (concerning the practice of medicine; care of a slave's child while she is in the field; sudden death of a slave mourned both as loss of property and as loss of a member of the family; and sale of slave " [?] will tell the negroes and send them to crying and howling."
      - Letters by Iverson L. Twyman (1810-1864), 1849., 11 items. (Folder 24)
        Includes letters to Frances Austin, Thomas Austin (concerning Rebecca Horsley), Grace B. Austin, Bernard Austin, Mrs. Martha E. Twyman, John Austin (hire of the slave Beverly; suggests taking him to a slave trader to see how much he would give for him to know whether to sell him or hire him out).
      - Letters by Iverson L. Twyman (1810-1864), 1850., 5 items. (Folder 25)
        Includes letters to Daniel Woodson, Glass & Woodson, Lynchburg, Va., Thomas Austin, John Austin. Advice to John Austin concerning the study of medicine. Selling of slaves.
      - Letters by Iverson L. Twyman (1810-1864), 1851., 19 items. (Folder 26)
        Includes letters to John Austin (writing a thesis for Austin while Austin is studying medicine in Philadelphia; hiring of slaves), Thomas Austin, Mrs. Martha E. Twyman.
      - Letters by Iverson L. Twyman (1810-1864), 1852-1853., 12 items. (Folder 27)
        Includes letters to Martha A. Twyman, Frances A. Austin (concerning hiring of slaves), John Austin, Thomas Austin, B. M. DeWitt (concerning family rift), M. M. Pendleton.
      - Letters by Iverson L. Twyman (1810-1864), 1854-1855., 15 items. (Folder 28)
        Includes letters to James M. Spiller, Thomas Austin (concerning sale of a slave child), Martha E. Twyman (concerning a division of slaves; advice on raising their son; selling slaves), B. M. DeWitt, W. M. Cabell, Iverson L. Twyman ([b. 1849] encouraging him to learn to read.)
      - Letters by Iverson L. Twyman (1810-1864), 1856-1860., 15 items. (Folder 29)
        Includes letters to James M. Spiller, Dr. Isaac Hays, R. S. Ellis, Dr. W. A Horsley (concerning cure for tapeworm), Orville Allen, Gen. Ro. A. Banks (politics), Gen. A. Brown, D. A. Snow (termination of a female schoolteacher's school because of her opinions on the hanging of the John Brown conspirators), Jno. Thompson.
      - Letters by Iverson L. Twyman (1810-1864), 1861-1864., 17 items. (Folder 30)
        Civil War comments in letters to Thomas Austin, J. M. Spiller, Iverson L. Twyman (b. 1849), J. B. McCaw (war injury of an Alabama soldier), Martha E. Twyman (concerning his illness and stay at Coyner's Springs), Col. R. H. Gilliam.
      - Letters by Iverson L. Twyman (1810-1864), n.d., 8 items. (Folder 31)
        Includes note concerning trying to make slaves look better before they are sold.
      - Letters to Iverson L. Twyman (1810-1864), 1829-1839., 14 items. (Folder 32)
        Seth Woodruff (buying slaves in Richmond and taking them south), P. G. Gillum (concerning medical studies in Philadelphia), W. N. Rodes (Tennessee life), Orville Allen, B. M. DeWitt, F. Hopkins.
      - Letters to Iverson L. Twyman (1810-1864), 1840-1842., 10 items. (Folder 33)
        Includes letters from F. Hopkins, Samuel Jackson (medical advice), Chas. P. Lee, George S. Thornton (study of medicine in Philadelphia), William H. Diggs.
      - Letters to Iverson L. Twyman (1810-1864), 1843-1844., 12 items. (Folder 34)
        Includes letters from B. M. DeWitt, F. Hopkins, John Early (1786-1873), Anthony Thornton, John H. Rodes, Lea & Blanchard, Philadelphia, Pa., Andrew White, Benjamin White.
      - Letters to Iverson L. Twyman (1810-1864), 1845., 5 items. (Folder 35)
        Includes letters from Benjamin F. Rodes, F. T. Stribling (superintendent of Western Asylum), A. Pamplin, Shelton F. Leake, and B. M. DeWitt.
      - Letters to Iverson L. Twyman (1810-1864), 1846., 17 items. (Folder 36)